spryker.com 2019-06-27

# Privacy Policy - Spryker

## SPRYKER SYSTEMS GMBH DATA PROTECTION POLICY

We thank you for your interest in our website. The protection of your personal information is very  
important to us. Below we shall communicate with you in detail about the handling of your data. If  
the processing of personal data is necessary and there is no legal basis for such processing, we  
generally obtain the user’s consent.  
The processing of personal data, such as the name, address, e-mail address or telephone  
number of a data subject, is carried out in accordance with the requirements of the General Data  
Protection Regulation (GDPR).

## I. Name and Address of Responsible Body

The body responsible with regards to the GDPR is  
**Spryker Systems GmbH** **  
****Julie-Wolfthorn-Str. 1** **  
****10115 Berlin** **  
****Telephone: +49 (30) 2084 98350  ** **  
****Website: www.spryker.com** **  
****E-Mail: legal@spryker.com**

## II. Name and Address of the Data Protection Officer

Spyker Systems GmbH’s Data Protection Officer is:

**JENTZSCH IT Rechtsanwaltsgesellschaft mbH**  
**Dr. Jana Jentzsch**  
**Alsterarkaden  13** **  
****20354 Hamburg**  
**E-Mail: mail@jentzsch-it.de**

Every user can contact our data protection officer or Spryker Systems GmbH at any time with any questions or suggestions regarding data protection at: [legal@spryker.com](mailto:legal@spryker.com) .

## III. Collection of General Data and Information

The Spryker Systems GmbH website collects a range of general data, personal data and information each time you or an automated system accesses it. This general data and information is stored in the log files of the server. The following can be collected: 

  *  the type of browser and version used,
  *  the operating system used by the accessing system,
  * the website from which an accessing system reaches our website,
  * the sub websites which are accessed via an accessing system on our website,
  * the date and time of access to the website
  * an internet protocol (IP) address,
  * the internet service provider of the accessing system and
  * other similar data and information used in the case of attacks on our information technology systems.

When using this data and information, Spryker Systems GmbH does not draw conclusions about you and does not collate your data with other personal data of yours. 

Rather, this information is needed in order to: 

  *  correctly deliver the contents of our website requested by you,
  * optimize the contents of our website as well as the advertising for these,
  * ensure the long-term functionality of our information technology systems and the technology of our website, and
  * to provide law enforcement agencies with the information necessary for law enforcement in the event of a cyber attack. This anonymously collected data and information is therefore statistically evaluated by Spryker Systems GmbH and with the aim of increasing data protection and data security in our company with the end goal of ensuring an optimal level of protection for the personal data we process.

## IV. Cookies

Some of our Internet pages use “cookies”. Cookies do not cause any damage to your computer and do not contain any viruses. Cookies serve to make our website more user-friendly, effective and secure. Cookies are small text files that are stored on your computer and saved by your browser.

Such cookies are not only set by Spryker itself, but also on its behalf by third parties such as Google (see below) or Facebook. In order to do this, these third-party companies place cookies which record usage data on the user’s computer on behalf of Spryker. 

This is regarding such data that can be collected, for example, while the user moves around the Spryker website or clicks on advertising. 

When you access the website from our data protection regulations, cookies are also set which are stored beyond your current visit to the website (your “session”). 

Ability to object: If the user does not want to use cookies or wishes to delete existing cookies, she can switch them off and remove them via her internet browser. More information on deleting or disabling cookies can be found in the help texts of the browsers used or on the Internet, for example, under the search words “Deactivate cookies” or “Delete cookies” (deletion instructions in [Microsoft Internet Explorer](https://support.microsoft.com/de-de/kb/278835). Deletion instructions in [Mozilla Firefox](https://support.mozilla.org/de/kb/cookies-loeschen-daten-von-websites-entfernen?redirectlocale=de&redirectslug=Cookies+l%C3%B6schen). Deletion instructions in [Safari](http://www.apple.com/support/?path=Safari/3.0/de/11471.html)). If the user decides to disable cookies, this can reduce the scope of the service and have a negative impact on the use of Spryker services.

Find more information about cookies and third-party services in our [Cookie Policy](https://spryker.com/cookie-policy/).

Cookies, which are necessary for the execution of the electronic communication process, are stored on the basis of Art. 6 para. 1 letter f GDPR. Spryker Systems GmbH has a legitimate interest in the storage of cookies for the technically error-free and optimized provision of its services. As far as other cookies (e.g., cookies for the analysis of your surfing behavior) are stored, these will be treated separately in this data protection policy.

## V. Data Protection for Applications and in Application Procedures

Spryker Systems GmbH collects and processes the personal data of applicants for the purpose of processing the application procedure. Processing may also be carried out electronically. This is particularly the case if an applicant sends corresponding application documents to Spryker Systems GmbH by electronic means, for example, by e-mail or via our applicant portal. 

This transmitted data is transmitted in encrypted form and stored in a database, which is operated by our company and our service provider Personio GmbH ([https://www.personio.de/](https://www.personio.de/)), Buttermelcherstr. 16, 80469 Munich. We have concluded an order data processing contract with Personio GmbH, which offers the personnel administration and application management software we use and stores data exclusively on ISO 27001-certified servers in Germany, in accordance with the requirements of the GDPR. This ensures that your personal data is processed exclusively in accordance with our instructions and that uniformly high standards apply with regard to data security.

If Spryker Systems GmbH concludes an employment contract with an applicant, the transmitted data will be stored for the purpose of processing the employment relationship in compliance with the statutory provisions. If Spryker Systems GmbH does not conclude an employment contract with the applicant, the application documents will be automatically deleted six months after communication of the rejection decision, provided that there are no other legitimate interests of Spryker Systems GmbH to the contrary. Other legitimate interests in this sense are, for example, a burden of proof in proceedings under the General Equal Treatment Act (AGG). 

If the applicant gives us permission to store the data she has submitted in the applicant pool, we will include this data in our applicant pool for a period of 2 years and then delete it. Only Spryker’s HR staff have access to this data.

## VI. Spryker Systems GmbH Newsletter

If you would like to subscribe to the newsletter offered on our website, we require an e-mail address from you as well as information that allows us to verify that you are the owner of the e-mail address provided and that you agree to receive the newsletter. Further data will not be collected or only on a voluntary basis. We use this data exclusively for the dispatch of the requested information and do not pass it on to third parties.

The data entered in the newsletter registration form will be processed exclusively on the basis of your consent (Art. 6 para. 1 letter a GDPR). You can revoke your consent to the storage of the data, the e-mail address and their use for sending the newsletter at any time, for example, via the “Unsubscribe” link in the newsletter. The legality of the data processing processes already carried out remains unaffected by the revocation.

The data you provide us for the purpose of subscribing to the newsletter will be stored by us until you unsubscribe from the newsletter and deleted after you unsubscribe from the newsletter. Data stored by us for other purposes (e.g., e-mail addresses for the member area) remain unaffected by this. You can also revoke the further sending of newsletters by sending an e-mail to [widerruf@spryker.com](mailto:widerruf@spryker.com).

## VII. Data Protection Regulations of Spryker Systems GmbH in Connection with the Free Offer of Digital Content

**Collected data and purpose of use**

We collect the following data from you if you wish to obtain digital content from us, e.g., White Paper, Case Studies, etc..

  1. Surname: personal user salutation in e-mails  
2\. First name: personal, gender-specific user salutation in e-mails   
3\. Business e-mail address: Confirmation of e-mail address and of the sending of digital content and offers  
4\. Professional title: Adaptation of the sent contents and offers to the user’s role / job title for reasons of relevance  
5\. Phone number (optional): this will be asked in order to be able to contact you if you tick the optional “I would like to be called and learn more about Spryker” checkbox.

**Data collection and use**  

  1. Sending the digital content requested by the user by e-mail:  
After submitting the form, we will send you an e-mail in which you can confirm your e-mail address and the download request for the corresponding content by clicking on the confirmation link. The confirmation link then refers you directly to the content requested in the form (e.g., White Paper, eBook, etc.).

  2. Sending other, similar content and offers by e-mail:  
If you have confirmed your e-mail address as described under number 1, we will send you other e-mails in the course of the following weeks which refer to other, similar digital content and offers from Spryker Systems GmbH. These are based on the content already requested, your role, and the size of the company. You can also revoke the future sending of content by sending an e-mail to [widerruf@spryker.com](mailto:widerruf@spryker.com).

## VIII. Participation Conditions for Spryker Systems GmbH Events and Training

**Data collection and use** **  
** The event organizer and/or Spryker Systems GmbH requires the participant’s personal data for the planning and execution of events. The participant agrees that his data may be processed and used for the initiation, implementation and follow-up of the event.

This consent applies in particular with regard to the following purposes:

  1. a) Invitation management by e-mail:

  * Sending of registration confirmations by e-mail
  * Sending of reminders by e-mail before the event
  * Sending of additional information or short-term changes to the registered event participants
  * Event planning optimization
  * Publication of participant lists (incl. names)
  * General contract initiation

The following data will be recorded:

  * E-mail address
  * Surname, first name
  * Sex
  * Job title
  * City
  * Telephone number (optional)

**Image rights** **  
** The participants of the event hereby declare their consent (free of charge) for the creation of images and video recordings of their persons during the events and to the use and publication of such images for the purpose of public reporting (in particular, print media or the internet) on the events. This also includes publication on Spryker homepages, Facebook, Google and other social media sites. 

Spryker is not liable for third parties using the images for other purposes without their knowledge, in particular by downloading and/or copying.

**Revocation** **  
** Furthermore, the participant has the right to revoke the consent given to Spryker Systems GmbH for processing and use in the future at any time.

## IX. Rights of Affected Persons

One of the objectives of the GDPR is to protect and clarify the data protection rights of EU citizens and users within the EU. This means that you as a user still have various rights with regard to your data, even if you have already given it to us. These rights are described in more detail below.

If you wish to contact us in connection with these rights, please contact our data protection officer (the contact details can be found under number II) or directly at legal@spryker.com We will aim to answer your request as quickly as possible, in any case within one month (extensions may be applied to which we are legally entitled). 

Please note that we may keep records of our communications in order to better resolve any problems you raise.

You have the following rights:

a)    Right to confirmation  
Every user of our website has the right to request confirmation from us as to whether we are processing his personal data. If the user wishes to make use of this right, he can contact our data protection officer at any time or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com.

b)    Right to information  
Every user has the right to receive information from us at any time, free of charge, about the personal data stored about him/her as well as a copy of this information. Furthermore, the user can obtain information about the following: purposes of processing  
•    the categories of personal data to be processed  
•    the recipients or categories of recipients to whom the personal data have been or are still being disclosed,   
•    if possible, the planned duration for which the personal data will be stored or, if this is not possible, the criteria for determining this duration  
•    the existence of a right of rectification or deletion of personal data concerning him or of a restriction on processing by the responsible party, or of a right of opposition to such processing  
•    the existence of a right of appeal to a supervisory authority  
•    if the personal data is not collected from the data subject: All available information about the origin of the data  
•    the existence of automated decision-making, including profiling in accordance with Article 22 para. 1 and 4 GDPR and, at least in these cases, meaningful information on the logic involved and the scope and intended effects of such processing for the data subject.

Furthermore, the user has the right to information as to whether personal data has been transferred to a third country or to an international organization. If this is the case, the user has the right to obtain information about the appropriate guarantees in connection with the transmission. If a user wishes to make use of this right to information, he or she can contact our data protection officer or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com at any time.

c)    Right to rectification  
Every user has the right to demand the immediate correction of incorrect personal data concerning him. Furthermore, the user has the right, taking into account the purposes of the processing, to request the completion of incomplete personal data, also by means of a supplementary declaration.  
If the user wishes to make use of this right to rectification, he can contact our data protection officer or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com at any time.

d)    Right to deletion (right to be forgotten)  
Every user has the right to demand from us that the personal data concerning her be deleted immediately, provided that one of the following reasons applies and insofar as processing is not necessary:

  * the personal data has been collected or otherwise processed for such purposes for which they are no longer necessary.
  *  the user withdraws his consent on which the processing was based pursuant to Article 6 para. 1 letter a GDPR or Article 9 para. 2 letter a GDPR, and there is no other legal basis for the processing.
  * the user objects to the processing in accordance with Article 21 para 1 GDPR and there are no overriding legitimate grounds for the processing, or the person concerned objects to the processing in accordance with Article 21 para. 2 GDPR.
  * the personal data has been processed unlawfully.
  * the deletion of personal data is necessary to fulfill a legal obligation under Union law or the law of the Member States to which Spryker is subject.
  * the personal data was collected in relation to information society services offered pursuant to Art. 8 para. 1 GDPR.

If one of the aforementioned reasons applies and a user wishes to have personal data that is stored with us deleted, she can contact our data protection officer or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com at any time. 

e)    Right to limitation of processing  
  
Every user has the right to request us to limit processing if one of the following conditions is met:

  * the accuracy of the personal data is disputed by the user for a period that enables us to verify the accuracy of the personal data.
  * the processing is unlawful, the user refuses to delete the personal data and instead requests the limitation of the use of the personal data.
  * Spryker no longer needs the personal data for the purposes of processing, but the user needs it to assert, exercise or defend legal claims.
  * the user has filed an objection to the processing according to Art. 21 para. 1 GDPR and it has not yet been determined whether Spryker’s justified reasons outweigh those of the user.

If one of the above conditions is met and the user wishes to request the limitation of personal data stored with us, he can contact our data protection officer or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com at any time.  

f)    Right to data transferability  
  
Every user has the right to receive the personal data concerning him, which was made available to us by the user, in a structured, current and machine-readable format. Furthermore, she also has the right to transmit this data to another responsible person without our interference, provided that the processing is based on the consent according to Art. 6 para. 1 letter a GDPR, or Art. 9 para. 2 letter a GDPR, or on a contract according to Art. 6 para. 1 letter b GDPR and the processing is carried out using automated procedures, provided that the processing is not necessary for the performance of a task in the public interest or in the exercise of public authority which has been transferred to us.  
In addition, when exercising their right to data transferability pursuant to Art. 20 para. 1 GDPR, the user has the right to ensure that the personal data be transferred directly from one responsible party to another responsible party, insofar as this is technically feasible and provided that the rights and freedoms of other persons are not affected by this.  
To assert the right to data transferability, the user can contact our data protection officer or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com at any time.

g) Right to object  
  
Every user has the right to object at any time to the processing of personal data concerning her on the basis of Art. 6 para. 1 letter e or f GDPR for reasons arising from her particular situation. 

h)    Right to revoke consent under data protection law  
  
Every user has the right to revoke his consent to the processing of personal data at any time.  
If a user wishes to exercise his right to revoke his consent, he can contact our data protection officer or contact us directly at legal@spryker.com at any time.

i) Right to appeal to a supervisory authority

The user has the right to file a complaint with the competent local supervisory authority. Details on how to contact the authority can be found here:

Freie und Hansestadt Hamburg  
Der Hamburgische Beauftragte für Datenschutz und Informationsfreiheit  
Prof. Dr. Johannes Caspar  
Klosterwall 6 (Block C), 20095 Hamburg  
Tel.: 040 / 428 54 – 4040  
Fax: 040 / 428 54 – 4000  
E-Mail: mailbox@datenschutz.hamburg.de

## X. Routine Deletion and Blocking of Personal Data

Spryker Systems GmbH processes and stores your personal data only for the period of time necessary to achieve the storage purpose or if this was provided for in laws or regulations to which Spryker Systems GmbH is subject.

If the storage purpose ceases to apply or if a storage period prescribed by law expires, the personal data will be routinely deleted or blocked and in accordance with the statutory provisions, provided that there are no storage obligations to the contrary.

## XI. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of HubSpot

Spryker Systems GmbH uses HubSpot for its online marketing activities. This is an integrated software solution with which we cover various aspects of our online marketing. We have concluded an order data processing contract with HubSpot in accordance with the requirements of the GDPR.

This includes, among other things:

  * E-mail marketing (newsletters and automated mailings, e.g., for the provision of downloads)
  * Social media publishing & reporting
  * Reporting (e.g., traffic sources, accesses, etc.)
  * Contact management (e.g., user segmentation & CRM)
  * Landing pages and contact forms

Our registration service allows users of our website to learn more about our company, download content, and provide their contact information and other demographic information. This information and the contents of our website are stored on servers of our software partner, HubSpot. We can use this information to contact users of our website and to determine which services of our company are of interest to them. All information we collect is subject to this data protection policy. We use all collected information exclusively for the optimization of our marketing measures. HubSpot is a software company from the USA with a branch in Ireland.

Contact: HubSpot, 2nd Floor 30 North Wall Quay, Dublin 1, Ireland, Telephone: +353 1 5187500.

HubSpot is certified under the terms of the EU–U.S. Privacy Shield Framework and is subject to the TRUSTe’s Privacy Seal and the U.S.–Swiss Safe Harbor Framework.

  * [More information from HubSpot regarding data protection regulations from HubSpot »](https://legal.hubspot.com/privacy-policy)
  * [More information from HubSpot regarding the EU data protection regulations »](https://legal.hubspot.com/data-privacy)
  * More information about the cookies used by HubSpot is found [here](https://knowledge.hubspot.com/articles/kcs_article/reports/what-cookies-does-hubspot-set-in-a-visitor-s-browser) & [here](https://knowledge.hubspot.com/articles/kcs_article/account/hubspot-cookie-security-and-privacy) »

If you generally do not want HubSpot to collect your data, you can prevent cookies from being saved at any time by changing your browser settings accordingly.

## XII. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of Wistia 

Videos from the online video provider Wistia are included on our website. Wistia is a service of Wistia, Inc., 17 Tudor Street, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA. Integration requires that Wistia can perceive users’ IP addresses. An IP address is required to send content to the user’s browser. The use of Wistia is in the interest of creating an appealing presentation of our online offers. This represents a legitimate interest within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 letter f GDPR. We have concluded an order data processing contract with Wistia Inc. in accordance with the requirements of the GDPR.

More information on data protection and the cookies used can be found on the internet at [http://wistia.com/privacy](http://wistia.com/privacy).

## XIII. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of Google Analytics (with Anonymization Function)

Spryker Systems GmbH has integrated the Google Analytics component (with anonymization function) on its website. Google Analytics is a web analytics service. Web analysis is the surveying, collation and evaluation of data regarding the behavior of visitors to internet sites. Among other things, a web analysis service collects data on which website a user came from (a “referrer”), which subpages of the website were accessed, or how often and for how long a subpage was viewed. A web analysis is mainly used to optimize a website and for cost-benefit analysis of Internet advertising.

The operating company of the Google Analytics component is Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy, Mountain View, CA 94043-1351, USA.

Spryker Systems GmbH uses the suffix “_gat._anonymizeIp” for web analysis via Google Analytics. By means of this addition, Google shortens and anonymizes the IP address of the user’s internet connection if our internet pages are accessed from a member state of the European Union or from another state party to the Agreement on the European Economic Area.

The purpose of the Google Analytics component is to analyze the flow of visitors to our website. Among other things, Google uses the data and information obtained to evaluate the use of our internet sites, to compile online reports for us that show the activities on our internet sites, and to provide other services in connection with the use of our internet sites.

Google Analytics places a cookie on the user’s information technology system. What cookies are has already been explained above. By placing the cookie, Google is enabled to analyze the use of our website. Every time one of the individual pages of this website–which is operated by Spryker Systems GmbH and on which a Google Analytics component has been integrated–is visited, the internet browser on the user’s information technology system is automatically prompted by the respective Google Analytics component to transmit data to Google for the purpose of online analysis. As part of this technical process, Google obtains knowledge of personal data, such as the IP address of the user, which Google uses, among other things, to trace the origin and clicks of the user and subsequently enable commission statements.

Cookies are used to store personal information, such as access time, the location from which access originated, and the frequency of visits to our internet sites by the user. Each time you visit our website, this personal data, including the IP address of the internet connection used by the user, is transmitted to Google in the U.S.A.. This personal data is stored by Google in the United States of America. Google may disclose personal data collected through the technical process to third parties.

The user can prevent the storing of cookies through our internet sites as already described above, at any time through a corresponding setting of the internet browser used, and thus permanently object to the storing of cookies. The use of such an internet browser setting would also prevent Google from placing a cookie on the user’s information technology system. In addition, a cookie already placed by Google Analytics can be deleted at any time via the internet browser or other software programs.

Furthermore, the user has the option to object to the collection of data generated by Google Analytics related to the use of this website as well as to the processing of this data by Google and to prevent this from happening. To do this, the user must download and install a browser add-on from the link https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout. This browser add-on informs Google Analytics via JavaScript that no data and information on visits to internet sites may be transmitted to Google Analytics. The installation of the browser add-on is considered an objection by Google. If the user’s information technology system is deleted, formatted or reinstalled at a later time, the user must reinstall the browser add-on to deactivate Google Analytics. If the browser add-on is uninstalled or deactivated by the user or another person within their control, it is possible to reinstall or reactivate the browser add-on.

We have concluded a data processing contract with Google based on the so-called EU standard contract clauses. More information and Google’s current data protection conditions can be found at [https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/](https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/)and at [http://www.google.com/analytics/terms/de.html](http://www.google.com/analytics/terms/de.html). Google Analytics is explained in more detail at this link[https://www.google.com/intl/de_de/analytics/](https://www.google.com/intl/de_de/analytics/).

## XIV. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of Google Maps

This website uses the map service Google Maps via an API. The provider is Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Parkway, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA.

To use the functions of Google Maps it is necessary to save your IP address. This information is usually transferred to a Google server in the USA and stored there. The provider of this website has no influence on this data transmission.

The use of Google Maps is in the interest of creating an appealing representation of our online offers and to ensure that the places indicated by us on the website are easy to find. This represents a legitimate interest within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 letter f GDPR.

You can find more information on the handling of user data in Google’s data protection policy: [https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/](https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/)

## XV. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of Google AdWords

Spryker Systems GmbH has integrated Google AdWords on this website. Google AdWords is an Internet advertising service that allows advertisers to place ads in both Google’s search engine results and the Google Advertising Network. Google AdWords allows an advertiser to pre-define certain keywords to display an ad in Google’s search engine results only when the user uses the search engine to retrieve a keyword-relevant search result. In the Google Advertising Network, ads are distributed on topical websites using an automated algorithm and according to pre-defined keywords.

The operating company for the Google AdWords service is Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy, Mountain View, CA 94043-1351, USA.

The purpose of Google AdWords is to promote our website by displaying interest-based advertising on third-party websites and in the search engine results of Google’s search engine and by displaying advertisements on our website.

If a user reaches our website via a Google ad, a so-called conversion cookie will be stored on the user’s information technology system by Google. What cookies are has already been explained above. A conversion cookie loses its validity after thirty days and is not used to identify the user. If the cookie has not yet expired, the conversion cookie is used to determine whether certain sub-pages, such as the shopping basket of an online shop system, have been called up on our website. The conversion cookie enables both us and Google to track whether a user who has accessed our website via an AdWords ad has generated revenue, that is, completed or canceled a purchase of goods.

The data and information collected through the use of the conversion cookie is used by Google to generate visit statistics for our website. We use these visit statistics to determine the total number of users who have been referred to us via AdWords ads, that is, to determine the success or failure of the respective AdWords ad and to optimize our AdWords ads for the future. Neither our company nor other Google AdWords advertisers receive information from Google that could identify the person concerned.

The conversion cookie is used to store personal information, such as the websites visited by the person concerned. Personal data, including the IP address of the Internet connection used by the person concerned, is therefore transferred to Google in the United States of America each time she visits our Internet pages. This personal data is stored by Google in the United States of America. Google may disclose personal data collected through the technical process to third parties.

The person concerned can prevent the storing of cookies by our website at any time, as already described above, through an appropriate setting on the internet browser used and thus permanently object to the storing of cookies. Use of such an internet browser setting would also prevent Google from storing a conversion cookie on the information technology system of the person concerned. In addition, a cookie already set by Google AdWords can be deleted at any time via the internet browser or other software programs.

Furthermore, the person concerned has the option to object to interest-based advertising by Google. To do this, the person concerned must access the link [http://www.google.de/settings/ads](http://www.google.de/settings/ads) from each of the Internet browsers they use and adjust the required settings there.

We have concluded a data processing contract with Google based on the so-called EU standard contract clauses. More information and the applicable data protection regulations from Google can be obtained at [https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/](https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/).

## XVI. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of Facebook

**Facebook Plugins (Like & Share Buttons)**

Our website includes plugins from the Facebook social network, provided by Facebook Inc., 1 Hacker Way, Menlo Park, California 94025, USA. You can recognize the Facebook plugins through the Facebook logo or the “Like” button on our page. An overview of the Facebook plugins can be found here: [https://developers.facebook.com/docs/plugins/](https://developers.facebook.com/docs/plugins/).

When you visit our website, the plugin establishes a direct connection between your browser and the Facebook server. Facebook receives the information that you have visited our site with your IP address. If you click the Facebook “Like” button while logged into your Facebook account, you can link the contents of our pages on your Facebook profile. This allows Facebook to associate the visit to our pages with your user account. We would like to point out that, as the provider of the pages, we have no knowledge of the content of the data transmitted or of its use by Facebook. For more information, please see Facebook’s data protection policy at: [https://de-de.facebook.com/policy.php.](https://de-de.facebook.com/policy.php.)

If you do not want Facebook to associate your visit to our pages with your Facebook account, please log out of your Facebook account.

## XIX. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of XING

We use components of the XING network on our website. These components are a service of XING AG, Dammtorstrasse 29-32, 20354 Hamburg, Germany.  
Each time you access our internet pages equipped with such a component, this component causes the browser you use to download a corresponding representation of the XING component.

To the best of our knowledge, XING does not store any personal user data when you visit our website. Neither does XING store any IP addresses. In addition, no evaluation of usage behavior takes place via the use of cookies in connection with the “XING Share Button”. For more information, please see the data protection information for the XING share button at: [https://www.xing.com/app/share?op=data_protection](https://www.xing.com/app/share?op=data_protection)

## XX. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of LinkedIn

Our Internet pages use a function of the LinkedIn network. The provider of this service is LinkedIn Corporation, 2029 Stierlin Court, Mountain View, CA 94043, USA. If you click the LinkedIn button (plugin), you will be redirected to our LinkedIn offer in a separate browser window, and if you are logged into your LinkedIn user account you can follow us at LinkedIn. The plug-in establishes a direct connection between your browser and the LinkedIn server. LinkedIn receives the information that you have visited our website with your IP address. In addition, LinkedIn will then be able to associate your visit to our website with you and your user account, provided you are logged into your LinkedIn user account. We point out that we have no knowledge of the content of the transmitted (personal) data and its use by LinkedIn. For more information, please see LinkedIn’s data protection policy: [https://www.linkedin.com/legal/privacy-policy](https://www.linkedin.com/legal/privacy-policy).

## XXI. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of YouTube

Our website uses plugins from Google’s YouTube site. The website is operated by YouTube, LLC, 901 Cherry Ave, San Bruno, CA 94066, USA.

If you visit one of our websites equipped with a YouTube plugin, a connection to the YouTube servers is established. This tells the YouTube server which of our websites you have visited.

If you’re logged into your YouTube account, YouTube will allow you to associate your browsing behavior directly with your personal profile. You can prevent this by logging out of your YouTube account.

The use of YouTube is in the interest of creating an attractive presentation of our online offers. This represents a legitimate interest within the meaning of Art. 6 para. 1 letter f GDPR.

For more information on how user data is handled, please see YouTube’s privacy policy: [https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy](https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy).

## XXII. Data Protection Regulations for the Use and Application of WhatsApp Broadcast

To provide the WhatsApp broadcast service, we use the services of WhatsBroadcast GmbH, Schwanthalerstrasse 32, 80336 Munich. If you visit one of our pages that is equipped with a WhatsApp plugin, a connection to the servers of WhatsBroadcast GmbH is established. This tells the WhatsBroadcast GmbH server which of our websites you have visited.  If you subscribe to a newsletter service via your Messenger, your phone number will be stored on the WhatsBroadcast GmbH servers. The data can be deleted at any time by sending the text “DELETE ALL DATA” via your Messenger.

More information on the handling of user data can be found in WhatsBroadcast GmbH’s data protection policy: [https://www.whatsbroadcast.com/de/datenschutz/](https://www.whatsbroadcast.com/de/datenschutz/)

## XXIII. Contact Form

When contacting us by e-mail or via a contact form, we store the data you provide in order to answer your questions. The data is deleted after storage is no longer required. If there are legal storage obligations, we shall restrict processing. We delete the data arising in this context after storage is no longer necessary, or limit processing if legal storage obligations exist.

## XXIV. Right of Modification

We reserve the right to change these data protection regulations at any time within the scope of applicable laws.
